Faculty of Education fonds
Simon Fraser University Archives and Records Management Department
- Publications, 1965 - 2005; F-233-7; 47 cm of textual records
  - Professional Programs publications, 1970 - 1999; F-233-7-3; 16 cm of textual records
    - Orientation information for PDP students, 1980 - 1982; F-233-7-3-0-11 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-361.
    - PDP program information, 1981; F-233-7-3-0-12 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-241.
    - PDP program information, 1981 - 1982; F-233-7-3-0-13 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Professional Development Program policies, procedures and services handbooks, 1981 - 1983; F-233-7-3-0-14 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Faculty Associate Newsletter, [1982?]; F-233-7-3-0-15 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - PDP program information, 1982 - 1983; F-233-7-3-0-16 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-236.
    - The Jargon Dictionary. Simon Fraser PDP, 1983; F-233-7-3-0-17 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - PDP registration package, 1983 - 1984; F-233-7-3-0-18 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-367.
    - PDP scholarship information, 1983 - 1985; F-233-7-3-0-19 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-372.
    - French Teacher Training (booklet), 1984; F-233-7-3-0-20 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - PDP program information, 1998 - 1999; F-233-7-3-0-21 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
  - Graduate Programs publications, 1971 - 2000; F-233-7-4; 4 cm of textual records
    Series consists of publications relating to the Graduate Programs division of the Faculty of Education. Records includes program information, brochures, handbooks, and the Graduate Programs newsletter (1997-1999).
    Faculty of Education. Graduate Programs
    For other records relating to the faculty's graduate programs, see the following series in this fonds:
    - F-233-3-8, Graduate Programs Committee files (1969-1994).
    - Graduate Programs information, [ca 1971] - [ca 1972]; F-233-7-4-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Graduate Studies in Education, [ca 1983]; F-233-7-4-0-2 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Graduate Programs brochures, 1995; F-233-7-4-0-3 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Graduate Programs newsletters, 1997 - 1999; F-233-7-4-0-4 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Graduate Programs information, 1998 - 1999; F-233-7-4-0-5 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Graduate Studies handbooks, 1998 - 1999; F-233-7-4-0-6 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
    - Graduate Studies handbooks, 2000; F-233-7-4-0-7 (Archival box - standard 233-66)
  - Undergraduate Programs publications, 1978 - 1984; F-233-7-5; 4 cm of textual records
    Series consists of publications relating to the Undergraduate Programs division of the Faculty of Education. Records include program information sheets, pamphlets, and booklets.
    Faculty of Education. Undergraduate Programs
    For other records relating to the faculty's undergraduate programs, see the following series in this fonds:
    - F-233-3-10, Undergraduate Programs Committee files (1972-1991).
    - Undergraduate Programs information, 1978 - 1981; F-233-7-5-0-1 (Archival box - small 233-61)
    - Undergraduate Programs and Courses, 1980; F-233-7-5-0-2 (Archival box - small 233-61)
    - Bachelor of Education booklet, 1983; F-233-7-5-0-3 (Archival box - small 233-61)
    - Undergraduate Programs information binder for summer 1984, F-233-7-5-0-4 (Archival box - small 233-61)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-365.
  - Field Programs publications, 2003 - 2005; F-233-7-6; 3 cm of textual records
    Series consists of publications relating to the services, events, conferences and workshops offered by the Field Programs division of the Faculty of Education. Records include pamphlets, brochures, and information sheets.
    Faculty of Education. Field Programs
    - Pamphlets, brochures, information sheets, 2003; F-233-7-6-0-1 (Archival box - small 233-61)
    - Pamphlets, brochures, information sheets, 2004; F-233-7-6-0-2 (Archival box - small 233-61)
    - Pamphlets, brochures, information sheets, 2005; F-233-7-6-0-3 (Archival box - small 233-61)
- Special media records, 1975 - 1998; F-233-8; 14 contact sheets 105 photographs 545 slides 55 sound recordings 3 moving images; General note: photographs are located in sub-series 1, moving images in sub-series 2, sound recordings in sub-series 3.
  Series consists of non-textual records (special media) created by the Faculty of Education and maintained separately from the textual files. Records include photographs, audio-visual recordings, and audio recordings.
  The series was established by the SFU Archives to bring together all non-textual materials kept apart from the textual records by the Faculty of Education. Sub- and sub-sub-series were established on the basis of media, format, or event.
  Sound recordings; Photographic materials; Textual records; Moving images
  Where the faculty integrated special media with related textual records (e.g. included photos or audio tapes in a file), these links have been maintained in the arrangement of the material. See the following series in this fonds for other special media:
  - F-233-1-1, Dean of Education correspondence (1965-1977), file 35 (architectural drawings).
  - F-233-3-3, Faculty Meeting files (1965-2000), items 1-4 (audio tapes).
  - F-233-5-1-1, Professional Programs Director's subject files (1968-1997), file 84 (photos) and items 5-6 (audio tapes).
  - Photographs collection, 1975 - 1989; F-233-8-1; 14 contact sheets 105 photographs 545 slides
    Series consists of photographic material relating to the Faculty of Education. Activities and subjects documented include the operations of the Learning Resources Centre ca. 1970s; portraits of staff, faculty, and faculty and school associates ca. 1980s; the 1982 faculty Christmas party; particular PDP courses; conferences; and faculty jubilee events (1989). Formats include black and white and colour prints, contact sheets, and slides.
    Material is organized in files arranged chronologically.
    Photoraphs were transferred from the faculty to the University Records Centre some time in the late 1980s. The records were appraised and scheduled in 1994 and were formally accessioned into the Archives in 1999.
    For other photographs in this fonds (integrated with textual records), see the following series:
    - F-233-5-1-1, Director's subject files (PDP program), file 84.
    File lists are available. An index to the photographs (contact sheets) in file 9 is included in the file. A list of slide subjects was prepared by the Archives in the 1980s, but it does not cross-reference the slide numbers and it is not possible to easily correlate the subjects and the actual slides; it has been included in file 14.
    - [Learning Resource Centre], [ca 1975]; F-233-8-1-0-1 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Photo album, 1976 - 1978; F-233-8-1-0-2 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-217.
    - Slides, [ca 1980]; F-233-8-1-0-3 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - [Administrators and staff portraits], [ca 1980] - [ca 1985]; F-233-8-1-0-4 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Slides, [ca 1981]; F-233-8-1-0-5 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Chrismas 1982, F-233-8-1-0-6 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Photographs - Faculty Associates, P.D.P., 1982 - 1983; F-233-8-1-0-7 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-22-8-7-0-486.
    - Slides, [ca 1982] - [ca 1989]; F-233-8-1-0-8 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - PDP program photographs, 1983 - [1986?]; F-233-8-1-0-9 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
      Photographic materials; Textual records
    - Education 483/484 slides, [ca 1985]; F-233-8-1-0-10 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - [Slides], [ca 1988] - [ca 1989]; F-233-8-1-0-11 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Campus conference, 1989; F-233-8-1-0-12 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Jubilee, 1989; F-233-8-1-0-13 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
    - Index to slides, [ca 1989]; F-233-8-1-0-14 (Archival box - standard 233-55)
  - Sound and moving images collection, 1972 - 1998; F-233-8-2; 30 moving image documents Analog originals: 11 16mm film reels 25 Umatic videocassette tapes 7 VHS videocassette tapes 7 Hi8 videocassette tapes
    Sub-series consists of films and videos created by or relating to the Faculty of Education. Includes a 1972 documentary on school-community interaction at Kitkatla (Gitxaala Nation) (item 1); Brent Reid's 1981 "SFU's Professional Development Program" (item 2); a 1998 discussion with faculty members John Ellis, Selma Wasserman, and Glenn Kirchner (item 3); a series of film and video works on physical education teaching directed by Glenn Kirchner (items 4-17); materials produced by Kirchner in collaboration with Brown & Benchmark Publishers for inservice programs for elementary school teachers (items 18-21); a 1981 production by BC's Provincial Educational Media Centre (item 22); and raw footage of a 1991 physical education class (items 23-30). Many of the pieces were produced with the assistance of SFU's Learning and Instructional Development Centre (LIDC) and its predecessors; contributions from Faculty and LIDC staff are noted in the item descriptions where known.
    Sub-series represents an artificial grouping created by the SFU Archives to bring together sound and moving image documents that were acquired as single items.
    Learning and Instructional Development Centre; Moving images
    Items were digitized in 2018, with copies in mkv format (preservation copy) and mp4 (access copy). Consult the reference archivist for information about access.
    Most items are open for offline access. A number are listed as "pending review" and must be reviewed by an archivist for personal information prior to release. Consult the reference archivist for more information.
    - Kitkatla: A Community Involvement in Education, 1972; F-233-8-2-0-0-1; 8 film reels 1 videocassette 1 .mov file (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-2437, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2789, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2790, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2791, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2792, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2793, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2794, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2795, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-2796)
      Item is a documentary about interaction and mutual involvement between school and community in Kitkatla (Gitxaala Nation). Made for SFU's Professional Development Centre with assistance from SFU's Audio Visual Centre, 1972. Directed by Peg Klesner, with contributions by Chris Hildred and Mary Louise Williams.
      Klesner, Peg; Hildred, Chris; Williams, Mary Louise; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized); Gitxaala Nation
      Duration: 28 minutes
      OBJ-2437 also available in .mkv and .mp4 formats.
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: 205.
    - Brent Reid: SFU's Professional Development Program (PDP), 1982; F-233-8-2-0-0-2 (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-2438)
      Reid, Brent; Moving images
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: F-233-item7.
    - A Dialogue with John Ellis, Selma Wassermann and Glenn Kirchner - Reflections on Three Decades in the Faculty of Education, May 1998; F-233-8-2-0-0-3 (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-2440)
      Produced by SFU's Learning and Instructional Development Centre, producers Linda Hof and Ian Andrews.
      Ellis, John F.; Wassermann, Selma; Kirchner, Glenn; Hof, Linda; Andrews, Ian; Moving images
      Duration: 45:15 minutes
      Open, offline access
      Previous reference code assigned by SFU Archives: 803.
    - Active Health Series: How the Heart and Circulatory System Works, 1982; F-233-8-2-0-0-4; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4171, Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5107)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with Elizabeth Carefoot (contributor), Chris Hildred (speaker), and Kurtis Vanel (sound mixing).
      Kirchner, Glenn; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Hildred, Chris; Vanel, Kurtis; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Physical Activity for Children, [197-?]; F-233-8-2-0-0-5; 1 videocassette 1 film reel (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4181, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-4195)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Chris Hildred, Frank Campbell, Wayne Carr, and Elizabeth Carefoot.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Campbell, Frank; Carr, Wayne; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Participation for All, [198-]; F-233-8-2-0-0-6; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4182, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4179)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner and Ian Andrews, with contributions by Chris Hildred, Wayne Carr, and John Dunn.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Andrews, Ian; Hildred, Chris; Dunn, John; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Physical Education Activities for the Classroom, [198-]; F-233-8-2-0-0-7; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4180)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner and Ian Andrews, with contributions by Chris Hildred, Wayne Carr, and Elizabeth Carefoot.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Andrews, Ian; Hildred, Chris; Carr, Wayne; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Teaching Games to Primary Children, [197-]; F-233-8-2-0-0-8; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4183, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4173)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Elizabeth Carefoot, Wayne Carr, John Dunn, Sherry Fulton, and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Carr, Wayne; Fulton, Sherry; Hildred, Chris; Dunn, John; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Teaching Game Activities to Intermediate Children, [198-?]; F-233-8-2-0-0-9; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4174, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4190)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Wayne Carr, John Dunn, Chris Hildred, and George Longstaff.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Carr, Wayne; Hildred, Chris; Longstaff, George; Dunn, John; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Introduction to Canoeing, [197-?]; F-233-8-2-0-0-10; 1 videocassette 1 film reel (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4172, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-4193)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, produced by School District No. 43, with contributions by Al Byers and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; School District No. 43; Byers, Al; Hildred, Chris; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Introduction to the Elements of Movement Education, [197-?]; F-233-8-2-0-0-11; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4184, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4176)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Wayne Carr, John Dunn, and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Carr, Wayne; Hildred, Chris; Dunn, John; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Using Small Equipment in Movement Education, [1976]; F-233-8-2-0-0-12; 2 videocassettes 1 film reel (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4175, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4185, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-4194)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Elizabeth Carefoot, Wayne Carr and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Carr, Wayne; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Hildred, Chris; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Using Large Apparatus in Movement Education, [1976]; F-233-8-2-0-0-13; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4186, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4177)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Wayne Carr, Elizabeth Carefoot, and Chris Hildred.
    - Theme Development in Movement Education, [197-?]; F-233-8-2-0-0-14; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4187)
    - Rhythmics: Movement to Music, [198-]; F-233-8-2-0-0-15; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4188, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4192)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner and George Longstaff, with contributions by Frank Campbell, Elizabeth Carefoot, Wayne Carr, Lou Crockett, and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Longstaff, George; Campbell, Frank; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Carr, Wayne; Crockett, Lou; Hildred, Chris; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Creative Folk Dance, [198-]; F-233-8-2-0-0-16; 1 videocassette 1 film reel (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4189, Film reel: 16mm OBJ-4215)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Al Byers, Frank Campbell, Elizabeth Carefoot, Wayne Carr, and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Byers, Al; Campbell, Frank; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Carr, Wayne; Hildred, Chris; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Orienteering, [197?]; F-233-8-2-0-0-17; 2 videocassettes (Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic OBJ-4191, Videocassette: 3/4&quot; umatic s (small) OBJ-4178)
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with contributions by Al Byers, Elizabeth Carefoot, Wayne Carr, and Chris Hildred.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Byers, Al; Carefoot, Elizabeth; Carr, Wayne; Hildred, Chris; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Teaching Folk Dance Activities, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-18; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5108)
      Moving image production shows how elementary children learn to keep time to a musical accompaniment, and the meaning of measure, accent, tempo, and musical phrase. Illustrates how children learn folk dances through a series of progressive steps. Shows how younger and older children learn to modify the dances they have learned by adding new steps, directions, and movement patterns. Designed for inservice programs for elementary school teachers.
      Contents:
      Understanding the elements of rhythm: Procedures to follow (Sitting and clapping; Travelling and clapping; Even rhythm) -- Using small equipment. Process used to teach folk dance: Step 1, Listen and move to music -- Step 2, Teach first part without music -- Step 3, Teach first part with music -- Step 4, Teach second part without music -- Step 5, Teach second part with music -- Step 6, Teach entire dance without music -- Step 7, Perform dance with music.
      Directed by Glenn Kirchner, with production assistance by Brown & Benchmark Publishers and Diane M. Smith.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Brown & Benchmark Publishers; Smith, Diane M.; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - Teaching Gymnastic Activities, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-19; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5109)
      Moving image production describes the similarities and differences between the content and teaching strategies used in traditional and educational gymnastics. Provides ideas and suggestions to illustrate how to integrate these two approaches according to the interest and background of each developmental level. Designed for inservice programs for elementary school teachers.
      Contents: Traditional gymnastics: Tumbling skills -- Balance skills -- Agility skills -- Small equipent -- Large apparatus. Teaching traditional gymnastics: Stress direct teaching method -- Teach according to progression (Headstand, Step 1-5) -- Use effective instructional techniques (Station work; Task).
    - Teaching Game Activities, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-20; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5110)
      Moving image production describes how game activities are organized and taught to children who fall within three developmental levels of motor skill. Includes suggestions for class organization, planning lessons, and the use of direct and problem-solving teaching strategies at each level. Designed for inservice programs for elementary school teachers.
      Contents: Developmental level 1. Game skills: Locomotor skills -- Manipulative skills (Control ball with hands; Control ball with feet; Project ball with implement). Content and teaching strategies: Variety of activities -- Progression -- Effective strategies (Good management skills; Positive teaching; Handicapped children). Developmental levels 2-3. Game skills -- Content and teaching strategies (Individual and team sports; Teaching strategies) -- Sample lesson plan (Entry activity; Introductory activity; Skill development; Closure).
    - Teaching Creative Dance Activities, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-21; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5111)
      Moving image production discusses the value and importance of a creative dance program. Describes the basic steps to follow when guiding young children to interpret ideas and feelings through creative dance activities. Stresses Laban's elements of movement. Designed for inservice programs for elementary school teachers.
      Step 1. Choosing a theme -- Step 2. Brainstorming -- Step 3. Exploring action words -- Step 4. Composing the dance -- Step 5. Performing the dance -- Step 6. Selecting ideas for future lessons.
    - Secondary Physical Education Curriculum, 1981; F-233-8-2-0-0-22; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5112)
      Item is a VHS recording of a program produced by BC's Provincial Educational Media Centre in conjunction with the Program Implementation Services Branch, Ministry of Education, to assist in implementing the Secondary Physical Education Curriculum (1980).
      Provincial Educational Media Centre; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
    - GK1/EDUC 5/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-23; 1 videocassette 1 .mkv file (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5114)
      Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
      .mkv file also available in .mp4 format.
    - GK2/EDUC 5/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-24; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5115)
      Moving images
    - GK3/EDUC 5/8/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-25; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5116)
    - GK5/EDUC 5/30/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-26; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5117)
    - GK6/EDUC 5/30/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-27; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5118)
    - GK7/EDUC Jun 7/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-28; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5119)
    - GK8/EDUC Jun 7/91, 1991; F-233-8-2-0-0-29; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: hi8 (metal-e) OBJ-5120)
    - Glenn teaching, May 27, 1998; F-233-8-2-0-0-30; 1 videocassette (Videocassette: vhs OBJ-5113)
      Item is a VHS recording of Glenn Kirchner teaching physical education instruction techniques.
      Kirchner, Glenn; Moving images; Records in electronic form (digitized)
  - Summer Institute on Teacher Education (SITE) lectures, 1983 - 1988; F-233-8-3; 39 sound recordings; Physical description: includes 41 audio cassettes.
    Sub-series consists of audio recordings (cassettes) of the public lectures presented as part of the Faculty of Education's annual Summer Institute in Teacher Education (SITE). Note that there are no recordings for 1986.
    Sub-series was arranged by the SFU Archives, with each year's institute forming a separate sub-sub-series. This sub-series incorporates material formerly arranged by the Archives as part of Record Group 100, "Audio tapes > Special Events" (RG-100/11).
    For posters of the Institutes, see series 7-1 (Faculty of Education publications), file 24.
    - SITE 1983: New Directions in Counselling and Education, F-233-8-3-1; 8 sound recordings; Physical description: includes 9 audio cassettes.